<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Katz Experiments</title><link>https://www.rkatz.xyz/</link><description>Recent content on The Katz Experiments</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 22:13:56 -0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.rkatz.xyz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The mix (and mess) of Packet Filter Linux - Part 1</title><link>https://www.rkatz.xyz/post/2020-09-13-the-mix-of-packet-filter-linux-part1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 22:13:56 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://www.rkatz.xyz/post/2020-09-13-the-mix-of-packet-filter-linux-part1/</guid><description>Introduction So you’ve got a brand new Linux distribution. You start your Kubernetes distributions, and decide for a specific CNI that provides network policies.
Then you figure out that something is (or is not) working, does an iptables -L to check what is going on and boom: where are all my iptables rules? Worst of all, you put some newer rules but they seem not to work and your traffic is still being blocked.</description></item><item><title>Flatcar Linux in VMware Player — 5 minute command line deploy</title><link>https://www.rkatz.xyz/post/2020-09-13-flatcar/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 20:28:50 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://www.rkatz.xyz/post/2020-09-13-flatcar/</guid><description>So I needed to create a new Kubernetes Lab. Back in time, I’ve created a shell script to deploy a lot of CoreOS servers to my VMware Player, but I hadn’t touched that script since that time.
With the deprecation of CoreOS and the glorious rise of Flatcar Linux to save us, and while needing to test some stuffs in Calico, it came to my mind ‘why not write how to quick deploy a Flatcar Linux VM in VMware Player without scripts?</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://www.rkatz.xyz/about/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.rkatz.xyz/about/</guid><description>Hello :) My name is Ricardo, I live in Sao Paulo since I was born in 1986. I do enjoy Lego, Airplanes (well, if I weren&amp;rsquo;t here in IT my dream was to be a pilot) and Kubernetes Stuff.
I work with Linux Administration (back when this wasn&amp;rsquo;t called SRE) since 2007, with some background also in security.
I&amp;rsquo;m the author of kubepug and you might see some bad bad coding practices, as this is my attempt to learn better Go coding :D</description></item></channel></rss>